An Inventory of the Elbridge Durbrow papers, 1926-1996
Hoover Institution Archives
Elbridge Durbrow papers,
1926-1996
85026
Durbrow, Elbridge, 1903-1997
71 manuscript boxes (28.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives
The collection documents the U.S. Foreign Service career and post-retirement of Elbridge Durbrow relating to the spread of communism, U.S. foreign policy and world politics following World War II, represented in the form of correspondence, clippings, interview transcripts, speeches and writings, press summaries, other printed material, and memorabilia. Consisting largely of Durbrow's writings, research materials, and correspondence, the collection reflects Durbrow's vast subject knowledge and expertise in foreign affairs.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Elbridge Durbrow Oral History, Columbia Center for Oral History, Columbia University Libraries
Oral History Interviews, Harry S. Truman Library and Museum
Lyndon Baines Johnson Oral History Collection, Lyndon Baines Johnson Library and Museum
Biographical Note
September 21, 1903 Born, San Francisco, California
1926 Bachelor of Arts, Philosophy, Yale University
1927-1929 Graduate studies at Stanford University and L'Académie de Droit International de la Haye; diploma in Sciences Politiques, École Libre des Sciences and Politiques
1930-1934 U.S. Vice-Consul, Warsaw, Poland and Bucharest, Romania
1934-1937 U.S. Vice-Consul, Moscow, U.S.S.R., The United States' first mission to the U.S.S.R.
1937-1939 U.S. Consul in Naples, Italy
1939-1940 Postgraduate work, University of Chicago
1940-1944 U.S. Consul, Rome, Italy, and Lisbon, Portugal
1944 Member of the U.S. delegation at the Bretton Wood Conference
1944-1946 Chief of the Eastern European Division, State Department
1946-1948 U.S. Deputy Chief of Mission, Moscow, U.S.S.R.
1948-1950 U.S. Deputy for Foreign Affairs and instructor, National War College
1950-1952 Division of Foreign Service Personnel, U.S. State Department
1952-1954 U.S. Deputy Chief of Mission, Rome, Italy
1955-1957 U.S. Minister and Consul General, Singapore
1957-1961 U.S. Minister and Consul General, Singapore
1961-1965 Alternate permanent representative to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization Council in Paris, France
1965-1968 Advisor to the commander of the Air University at Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama
1968 Retired from the State Department
1971 Director, Center for International Strategic Studies and the Freedom Studies
1976 Chairman, American Foreign Policy Institute
1977 President, Security and Intelligence Fund
May 16, 1997 Died, Walnut Creek, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The majority of the collection focuses on the materials used by Durbrow in the research for his writings, speeches, and lectures on foreign affairs before and after retirement. The main themes in his work relate to the spread of and adherence to communism throughout the world after World War II, and the United States' policies and relations with the Soviet Union. Excerpts from various books, articles and essays on the subjects of communism, the Soviet Union and the Cold War used by Durbrow in his research can also be found throughout the collection.
The papers include notes, outlines, drafts, and final versions of Durbrow's writings, speeches, and lectures. The bulk of the material dates from after Durbrow's retirement from the U.S. Foreign Service, when he became involved in foreign policy and national security think tanks, continuously researching, writing, and lecturing on foreign affairs.
Throughout the collection there are notes related to research topics, lectures, speeches, and writings, along with annotations on most clippings. In addition there are transcripts of radio and television interviews given by Durbrow; along with interviews for oral history projects at Columbia University, Lyndon Baines Johnson Oral History Collection and the Harry S. Truman Library.
Accompanying these materials is correspondence pertaining to Durbrow's writings, research, and personal matters. In particular, there is correspondence with prominent figures of the time: George Kennan, Clare Booth Luce, Walter Cronkite, William F. Buckley Jr., Ronald Reagan, and Spiro Agnew.
Security and Intelligence Foundation.; United States--Dept. of State.; Soviet Union--Economic conditions.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World politics--1945-1989.
- Clippings relating to communism in Latin America, Spain, Portugal, France and Italy, 1973-1979. (Box 1)
  In English and French
- Printed material and photocopies, 1974-1976, undated (Box 1)
- "Communism, Italian Style," 60 Minutes broadcast transcript, 1976 (Box 1)
- Rockefeller speech to the National Broadcasting Editorial Association Annual Meeting, 1976 (Box 1)
- International press summaries, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
- Le Monde interview with Jean Sauvagnargues, 1975 (Box 1)
- French Embassy press releases, and statements by Valéry Giscard D'Estaing, President of the France, relating to European Summit Meeting, 1974 (Box 1)
- Italian election notes, 1976 (Box 1)
- European communism document photocopy, 1947 (Box 1)
- "Highlights of Allende's Rise to Power," by Durbrow, undated (Box 1)
- "The Kremlin European Plans for 1976," by Durbrow, undated (Box 1)
- "Implementation of the 1969 'Popular Unity' Formula in Iceland, Norway, France, Italy and Spain," by Durbrow, circa 1975 (Box 1)
- "Angolan Awards for Tunney and Clark?" by Lee Roderick, 1976 (Box 1)
- Clippings relating to communism in Latin America, Spain, Portugal, France, and Italy, 1967-1979 (Box 2)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
- International press summaries, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
- Drafts by Durbrow, circa 1975 (Box 2)
  - "Highlights of Portugal's Left Take-Over,", circa 1975 (Box 2)
  - "Implementation of the 1969 Popular Unity Formula in Iceland, Norway, France, Italy and Spain,", circa 1975 (Box 2)
  - "General Antonio de Spinola - New Strongman?", circa 1975 (Box 2)
- "Allende in Retrospect," by Paul E. Sigmund, 1974 (Box 2)
- Clippings relating to European communism in Spain and Portugal, 1974-1978 (Box 3)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1975, 1977 (Box 3)
- International press summaries, 1974-1975, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
- Clippings, 1963, 1974-1976, 1978-1981, 1984 (Box 4)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1969, 1979-1980, 1982 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1974, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
- Ambassador James E. Akins address, transcript, 1979 (Box 4)
- International press summaries, 1970, 1974, 1978-1982 (Box 4)
- U.S. government reports and press releases photocopies, 1956, 1959, 1968, 1981 (Box 4)
- Memoranda, 1971, undated (Box 4)
- Drafts by Durbrow, 1979, 1981, undated (Box 4)
  - "Use of Positive Non-Military Means to Roll Back the Growth of Communism,", 1979 (Box 4)
  - "Summary of Diverse Soviet Methods of Operation,", 1981 (Box 4)
  - "Detente's Triple Threat ? Soviet Linkage,", undated (Box 4)
- "'The Movement': Role of the U.S. Activists," by Frank M. Watson, undated (Box 4)
- "Hanoi's Intensified Aggression - 1959," by Durbrow, 1967 (Box 4)
- "How We Help Moscow Advance" by Durbrow, undated (Box 4)
- "Agreement Between the United States and the Soviet Union Concerning Liberated Prisoners of War and Civilians," photocopy, circa 1946 (Box 4)
- "Why the Soviet Union Thinks It Could Fight and Win a Nuclear War," by Richard Pipes, 1977 (Box 4)
- "The Powell Memorandum," by Lewis F. Powell, 1971 (Box 4)
- Clippings relating to NATO, SALT talks, and Soviet Union disinformation tactics, 1975-1978 (Box 5)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
- Correspondence photocopies, 1977 (Box 5)
- International press summaries, 1975-1978 (Box 5)
- U.S. government press releases, undated (Box 5)
- Aleksandr Y. Bovin interview, transcript, 1976 (Box 5)
- U.S. Representative Jack Kemp statement on Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT) to the American Security Council photocopy, 1977 (Box 5)
- AFL-CIO platform proposals presented at Democratic and Republican National Conventions photocopy, 1976 (Box 5)
- "Détente as a Weapon of Soviet Policy," by John Eppstein, 1976 (Box 5)
- Clippings relating to Soviet Union disinformation tactics, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1976-1977 (Box 6)
- International press summaries photocopies, 1976-1978 (Box 6)
- Correspondence photocopy, 1977 (Box 6)
- University of Miami Center for Advanced International Studies press release, undated (Box 6)
- Clippings relating to NATO and détente, 1976-1979 (Box 7)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1965, 1976-1979 (Box 7)
- International press summaries, 1976-1978 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box 7)
- Memoranda photocopies, 1977 (Box 7)
- "A Conflict Situation," by Durbrow, undated (Box 7)
- Clippings relating to Soviet Union disinformation tactics, 1966, 1968-1979 (Box 8)
- Correspondence, 1976, 1979 (Box 8)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1972, 1976-1977, 1979 (Box 8)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1956, 1968, 1976 (Box 8)
  Includes photocopies
- International press summaries, 1976-1979 (Box 8)
- Vice President Rockefeller speech to the National Broadcasting Editorial Association Annual Meeting, 1976 (Box 8)
- "The Nature of National Dialogue" speech by Kissinger, 1973 (Box 8)
- "The Politics of MBFR" by James Sattler, 1973 (Box 8)
- Clippings relating to the 25th congress of the Communist Party and disinformation, 1973, 1975-1976 (Box 9)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1976 (Box 9)
- International press summaries, 1976 (Box 9)
- "Communism, Italian Style," 60 Minutes broadcast, transcript, 1976 (Box 9)
- BBC's Panorama with Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, transcript, 1976 (Box 9)
- Aleksandr Y. Bovin interview, transcript, 1976 (Box 9)
- Radio Liberty research documents, 1976 (Box 9)
- AFL-CIO executive council statement on Western Europe and National Communism, 1976 (Box 9)
- Clippings relating to the new communist movement, 1974, 1976-1977, 1979, 1981 (Box 10)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1965, 1968-1972, 1974-1976, 1978-1984 (Box 10)
- U.S. government report, 1981 (Box 10)
- International press summaries, 1976, 1978 (Box 10)
- Drafts by Durbrow, undated (Box 10)
  - "Dezinformatsia,", undated (Box 10)
  - "Détente's Triple Threat,", undated (Box 10)
  - "The Unseen Revolution,", undated (Box 10)
  - "A New U.S. Strategy for Peace and Freedom,", undated (Box 10)
- Frank H. Perez address before the Conference on Violence and Extremism, transcript, 1981 (Box 10)
- "Not in Vain" based on an independent fact-finding mission to South Vietnam by Durbrow, 1974 (Box 10)
- Clippings, 1977-1979 (Box 11)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1977-1979 (Box 11)
- Memorandum photocopy, 1949 (Box 11)
- U.S. government reports photocopies, 1979 (Box 11)
- International press summaries, 1978-1979 (Box 11)
- Draft notes, 1973-1974, 1983-1984, undated (Box 11)
- Correspondence, 1978 (Box 11)
- Memorandum photocopy, 1949 (Box 11)
- "CIA and the Press" by John M. Maury, undated (Box 11)
- Clippings, 1976-1977, 1979-1981 (Box 12)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1977, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
- Correspondence photocopies, 1977, 1980 (Box 12)
- International press summaries, 1975-1977, 1979-1981 (Box 12)
- Secretary of State Henry Kissinger's testimony at SALT II hearings before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1979 (Box 12)
- General Alexander Haig remarks at SALT II hearings by the Armed Services Committee, 1979 (Box 12)
- Walter Slocombe statement before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, transcript, 1979 (Box 12)
- CIA report on Soviet propaganda operations photocopy, 1978 (Box 12)
- Clippings relating to communist China and the Soviet- Czechoslovak crisis, 1968-1972, 1976-1979 (Box 13)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1958, 1965-1966, 1971, 1977-1978. (Box 13)
- International press summaries, 1972, 1976-1977 (Box 13)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1968, 1976, 1978 (Box 13)
- David Kennedy statement, 1979 (Box 13)
- Ambassador Leonard Unger's statement before House Foreign Affairs Committee, circa 1979 (Box 13)
- Treaty between the United States and Republic of China, excerpt, undated (Box 13)
- President Johnson question responses at various news conferences, 1966 (Box 13)
- Secretary Rusk address before the Veterans of Foreign Wars, responses at news conferences and news interviews, 1965-1966 (Box 13)
- Secretary of State Dean Rusk "United States Policy toward Communist China,", 1966 (Box 13)
- Clippings relating to U.S. policy in Southeast Asia, 1966 (Box 14)
- Printed material, 1945, 1957, 1962, 1964-1966, undated (Box 14)
- Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 14)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1961, 1965-1967 (Box 14)
- Secretary of State, Dean Rusk speech in San Francisco, 1968 (Box 14)
- Deputy Undersecretary of State, U. Alexis Johnson, address delivered at West Point, 1966 (Box 14)
- Ambassador Arthur J. Goldberg statement to the United Nations, 1966 (Box 14)
- U. Alexis Johnson speaking notes for address to Fulbright grantees, 1966 (Box 14)
- French Embassy press release on address by French Minister of Foreign Affairs before the 21st session of the United Nations, 1966 (Box 14)
- Warfare Systems School schedule, undated (Box 14)
- Organizational chart for United States Embassy in Vietnam, undated (Box 14)
- Drafts by Durbrow, undated (Box 14)
  - "The Most Critical Issues Facing the United States Today,", undated (Box 14)
  - "U.S. National Objectives and Strategy,", undated (Box 14)
  - "United States Foreign Policy Objectives,", undated (Box 14)
  - "The Importance of NATO,", undated (Box 14)
  - "Regional Organzations,", undated (Box 14)
- Speech outlines by Durbrow, 1967, undated (Box 14)
  - "U.S. Policy in Vietnam,", undated (Box 14)
  - "United States Policy in Asia: An Appraisal,", undated (Box 14)
  - "U.S. National Objectives and Strategy,", undated (Box 14)
  - "U.S. Foreign Policy Goals in Asia,", 1967 (Box 14)
  - "Critical International Issues,", undated (Box 14)
  - "Regional Organizations,", 1967 (Box 14)
  - "The Importance of the United Nations As It Becomes of Age,", undated (Box 14)
- Clippings, 1966-1968, 1971-1973, 1975-1977, 1979 (Box 15)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1966, 1969-1970, 1973-1974, 1976 (Box 15)
- Correspondence, from Stalin to Comrade Ivanov, 1938 (Box 15)
  Translated photocopy
- International press summaries, 1973, 1975-1976, 1978-1979 (Box 15)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1939, 1966, 1970, 1972 (Box 15)
- Foy D. Kohler speech, 1950 (Box 15)
- President Kennedy speeches, 1962-1963 (Box 15)
- "Economic Justice through Free Enterprises," speech delivered by Durbrow at 6th Regional Conference of Asia Junior Chamber International luncheon, 1956 (Box 15)
- 6th Regional Conference of Asia Junior Chamber International luncheon programme, 1956 (Box 15)
- Documents relating to the Conference of European Communist and Workers' Parties, 1967 (Box 15)
- "The United States Commercial Agreement with the Soviet Union," by Robert B. Wright, undated (Box 15)
- "Détente" draft by Durbrow, undated (Box 15)
- Radio Liberty research documents, 1979 (Box 15)
- Clippings, 1943, 1948-1949 (Box 16)
- Correspondence, 1949, 1951 (Box 16)
- Memoranda, 1949 (Box 16)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1940-1943, 1946, 1948-1950, 1955 (Box 16)
- Printed material, 1949 (Box 16)
- George F. Kennan speech to the Russian Institute student group, 1950 (Box 16)
- Field Marshall Jan Smuts, Prime Minister of South Africa, speech to the United Kingdom branch of the Empire Parliamentary Association, 1943 (Box 16)
- "The Great Contradiction in Russia," by Durbrow, 1949 (Box 16)
- William C. Bullitt address given before the Annual Convention of Federal Union, 1943 (Box 16)
- "The Role of Money in a Collectivist State," draft by Durbrow, 1940 (Box 16)
- Clippings, 1944-1947, 1973-1975, 1978-1979 (Box 17)
- Printed material, 1946-1947, 1979 (Box 17)
- International press summaries, 1946-1947 (Box 17)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1944-1946 (Box 17)
- Radio bulletins, 1945-1946 (Box 17)
- Document on U.S. relations relating to the Baltic States, 1944 (Box 17)
- Document on U.S. relations relating to Poland, 1944 (Box 17)
- Translation of cable between Polish Embassy in Moscow to Polish Military of Foreign Affairs in London, 1943 (Box 17)
- John Daniel Langer, untitled draft relating to the United States' lend-lease policy with the Soviet Union, undated (Box 17)
- "Harry Truman," by Boris Gorbatov, 1947 (Box 17)
  Translated in to English
- V. M. Molotov statement to representatives of the Soviet and foreign press, 1944 (Box 17)
- Convention for the Definition of Aggression, 1933 (Box 17)
- Treaty of Friendship between Afghanistan and the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic, with Supplementary Clause, 1921 (Box 17)
- Clippings relating to Persian Gulf, oil prices and NATO, 1965-1971, 1973-1976. (Box 18)
- Printed material, 1967, 1975 (Box 18)
- International press summaries, 1973-1975 (Box 18)
- "Yemen and South Yemen," draft by Durbrow, undated (Box 18)
- Clippings, 1973-1977 (Box 19)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1973-1975, 1977 (Box 19)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1973 (Box 19)
- Correspondence photocopies, 1974, 1976 (Box 19)
- French Embassy press release, 1973 (Box 19)
- International press summaries, 1973-1977 (Box 19)
- "The Middle East and Détente: A Rational Alternative to Current U.S. Policy,", 1974 (Box 19)
- Clippings relating to the Arab-Israeli conflict, 1968-1975, 1979 (Box 20)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1974, 1979 (Box 20)
- International press summaries, 1973-1974, 1979 (Box 20)
- Israeli press comment on U.S. commitments in Indochina, 1975 (Box 20)
- U.S. government reports, 1973, 1979 (Box 20)
- "The Radical Intellectual and U.S. Foreign Policy," by David S. Lichtenstein, undated (Box 20)
- Clippings relating to the Middle East crisis, 1967, 1977-1980 (Box 21)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1974, 1977-1980 (Box 21)
- International press summaries, 1977-1980 (Box 21)
- U.S. government reports, 1967 (Box 21)
- Radio Free America broadcast, transcript, 1978 (Box 21)
- National Geographic map of the Middle East, 1978 (Box 21)
- Chronology of events relating to the Middle East crisis, 1966-1967 (Box 21)
- "Castro's African Adventure," by Herminio Portello-Vidá, undated (Box 21)
- Clippings, 1971-1972, 1973-1975, 1979-1980 (Box 22)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1972, 1975, 1979 (Box 22)
- International press summaries, 1972-1975, 1979-1980 (Box 22)
- Correspondence and memoranda, 1969, 1972, 1979 (Box 22)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1972-1973 (Box 22)
- Telegram to Senator Edward Kennedy from John M. Fisher, 1969 (Box 22)
- Washington Report of the Air broadcast with Durbrow relating to the "Sihanouk Secret," transcript, 1973 (Box 22)
- French Embassy press releases relating to Brezhnev's visit to Paris photocopies, 1971 (Box 22)
- "Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe and Negotiations on Mutual and Balanced Force Reductions," Atlantic Council report, 1972 (Box 22)
- General A.J. Goodpaster address to the Heidelberg chapter association of the U.S. Army, 1972 (Box 22)
- "MBFR and the Soviet Union's Double Shift in Strategy," by James F. Sattler, undated (Box 22)
- "CSCE, MBRF, SALT II and the Politics of Europe," by Andrew J. Pierre, 1973 (Box 22)
- Clippings, 1972-1975 (Box 23)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1972, 1974 (Box 23)
- International press summaries, 1973-1975 (Box 23)
- U.S. government reports, 1973-1974 (Box 23)
- "Détente - How Realistic?" by Durbrow, undated (Box 23)
- "The Declaration of Renewed Cold War," draft by Durbrow, undated (Box 23)
- "Nuclear Deterrence and the Forces Needed for It," by Herbert F. York, 1973 (Box 23)
- ABC Evening News Howard K. Smith commentary, transcript, 1973 (Box 23)
- "Solzhenitsyn," CBS News Special, transcript, 1974 (Box 23)
- Eugene V. Rostow, the chairman of foreign policy task force of the Coalition for a Democratic Majority, address, 1974 (Box 23)
- Clippings relating to the capitalist crisis, 1973-1975 (Box 24)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1969, 1974-1975 (Box 24)
- International press summaries, 1974-1975 (Box 24)
- Reed J. Irvine remarks at A. J. Liebling Counter-Convention, New York City, 1974 (Box 24)
- "The Quest for Détente," by Task Force on Foreign Policy of the Coalition for a Democratic Majority, 1974 (Box 24)
- "The Threat," by Dr. Léon Gouré, 1974 (Box 24)
- "Communist Post Vietnam Cease-Fire Plans," by Durbrow, speech outline, 1973 (Box 24)
- Drafts by Durbrow, undated (Box 24)
  - "War, Cold War, and Détente ? All Pay Well,", undated (Box 24)
  - "Despite Allende's Fall,", undated (Box 24)
  - "Popular Unity Moves Forward,", undated (Box 24)
- "Détente and the 1969 Directive," by Jill D. Dorn, 1973 (Box 24)
- "1973 and Beyond," by Durbrow (Box 24)
- Clippings, 1970-1971, 1974 (Box 25)
- Printed material, 1969 (Box 25)
- International press summaries, 1974 (Box 25)
- U.S. government reports, 1974 (Box 25)
- "Renewed Cold War - Wars of National Liberation," draft by Durbrow, undated (Box 25)
- Clippings to the capitalist crisis and the future of communism, 1964-1971, 1973-1975 (Box 26)
- Correspondence photocopy, 1974 (Box 26)
- Memoranda, 1974 (Box 26)
- Printed material, 1964, 1967-1971, 1974 (Box 26)
- International press summaries, 1973-1974 (Box 26)
- U.S. government reports and press releases, 1958-1959, 1965, undated (Box 26)
- Nikita Khrushchev speech excerpt, 1961 (Box 26)
- First Deputy Chairman of the Council of Ministers of the USSR, L. M. Kaganovich speech, 1955. Translated into English (Box 26)
- "Marx and the Transformation of Man," by Gerhart Niemeyer, 1965 (Box 26)
- Drafts by Durbrow, undated (Box 26)
  - "Détente ? How Realistic,", undated (Box 26)
  - "Hot War, Cold War, and Détente ? All Pay Well,", undated (Box 26)
- Clippings relating to the future of communism, 1969-1972, 1974-1975 (Box 27)
- Printed material, 1969-1971, 1975, undated (Box 27)
- International press summaries, 1974-1975 (Box 27)
- U.S. government reports, circa 1967 (Box 27)
- Radio Liberty research documents, 1975 (Box 27)
- CBS Reports broadcast "The Selling of the Pentagon," transcript, 1971 (Box 27)
- "The Quiet World Revolution," draft by Durbrow, 1975 (Box 27)
- Clippings, 1971, 1973, 1985 (Box 28)
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box 28)
  Includes photocopies in English and Spanish
- Memorandum photocopies, 1945 (Box 28)
- Printed material and photocopies, 1965, 1969-1974, 1976, 1978, 1980-1984, undated (Box 28)
- International press summaries, 1969, 1973 (Box 28)
- NATO press release, 1971 (Box 28)
- Frank Johnson speech on "Détente and the National Debate,", circa 1972 (Box 28)
- Washington Report of the Air broadcasts with Durbrow, transcript, 1973, 1975 (Box 28)
- "Not in Vain," based on an independent fact-finding mission to South Vietnam by Durbrow, 1974 (Box 28)
- Outlines by Durbrow, 1981, undated (Box 28)